# Vivekpandian Veerapandian

San Jose, CA (214) 802-4843 github.com/vivekpandian08

vivekpandian08.github.io linkedin.com/in/vivekpandian8 vivekpandian08@gmail.com medium.com/@vivekpandian08

**Data Scientist** with **4 years of experience** in extracting customer and marketing insights from data points by building Linear and Non-Linear ML models. Established a \$25k revenue E-commerce business by recommending data-driven solutions.

#### **EDUCATION**

The University of Texas at Dallas - M.S., Business Analytics (Data Science Specialization), 3.67

Jan 2019 – Dec 2020

• Mentored 15 Grad Students for ML Project competition, and **secured 3rd place**. Built end to end regression model, developed web app using FLASK that predicts house price and hosted the app in the cloud using AWS.

College of Engineering Guindy, India - B.E., Electronics and Communication

Aug 2007 – May 2011

#### **TECHNICAL SKILLS**

Programming: Python (Scikit-learn, Pandas, Numpy, TensorFlow, PyTorch, Keras, Spacy, PySpark), R, SQL, SAS

Visualization: Tableau, Power BI, Shiny, Plotly, Streamlit

Databases & Bigdata: Snowflake, MySQL, PostgreSQL, Oracle, MongoDB (NoSQL), Hadoop, Hive, Spark

### **WORK EXPERIENCE**

**SuperWorld**, United States – Augmented Reality Real Estate on Blockchain

**Data Science Intern** | R

Sept 2020 - Present

• Developed an interactive web app in R-shiny that does real-time end to end sentiment analysis of SuperWorld's tweets

Ordermycake.in, India – E-Commerce B2C Platform to sell Bakery Products

Senior Data Scientist | Python, Tableau, AWS EC2, S3

Oct 2016 - June 2018

- Generated 18% increase in revenue to \$5k in 2017 by leveraging NLP techniques to analyze customers feedback
- Recommended optimized price for products by web scraping and data mining to analyze competitor product prices, leading to a \$3K increase in yearly revenue
- Designed 3 A/B tests to identify the most engaging marketing campaign, resulted in a 30% increase in sales and examined
  8 layouts and designs, increased Add to Cart rate to 40%
- Led a 10-member cross-functional team to build an end to end B2C platform to expand the **operations from 2 to 8 cities** and presented reports to stakeholders using **Tableau** charts and dashboards

**Data Scientist** | R, Python

Jan 2015 – Sep 2016

- Identified **4500 potential churn customers** by developing ML models using Logistic Regression, Decision Tree and **mitigated 36%** by offering them discounts
- Initiated a new payment method to solve delivery problems that satisfied customers and increased unit sales to 6.5%
- Revamped coupon mailing strategy for 3 customer segments by clustering using **K-means** and identifying the most engaging coupons leading to a **12% estimated increase in headcount**
- Built machine learning pipelines using python, optimized XGBoost model by adding new features to improve precision rate to 76% for the likelihood of purchase by analyzing consumer behavior

- Designed SQL queries to extract information from IoT sensor data and identified anomalies by K-means clustering
- Analyzed product pain points and collaborated with a multi-functional team to develop robust solutions to meet client requirements, increased project conversion to 30%

## PERSONAL PROJECTS (MACHINE LEARNING)

Can I predict your food? Maybe I Can! | Android SDK, Python (Deep Learning, GPU)

Sept 2020 - Present

- Gathering food images using JavaScript Console Window and python, and labeling by "LabelImg" annotation tool
- Building a prototype that takes data from users and does end to end ML to classify foods using TensorFlow Lite

**Uber Tweet Analysis** | Python (Natural Language Processing, Unsupervised Learning)

Mar 2020 – July 2020

Data mined 5 years Uber tweets using Tweepy, stored in MongoDB, cleaned and processed data by establishing an ETL pipeline, and identified 3 key topics that customer mentioning using LDA algorithm and achieved coherence score of 0.36

**Credit Card Fraud Detection** | Python (Supervised Learning)

May 2019 – July 2019

• Performed quantitative analysis, and hypothesis testing. Built an ML pipeline in PySpark to predict fraud transaction using SVM, KNN, Naïve Bayes Random Forest, and Neural Networks with **SMOTE** resampling and achieved AUC of 0.82